-[Narrator] Welcome to Module 2 Accessible Microsoft Word
Documents. In this video, you will learn how to
make your Microsoft Word documents accessible to
all learners.
In this section, we will set your document title
and language.
To set a document title in Microsoft Word, you will
click File, then select Info. From the right-hand
panel, locate the Properties section. Click on the
space indicated to the right of Title. Enter a
descriptive title here, such as "Accessibility
Training Module 1.0."
To set the document language, go to the Review tab.
Select Language, and choose Set Proofing Language.
From the list, select your desired language, such
as English (United States). Check the box labeled,
"Do not check spelling or grammar," and then click
OK to apply your settings. Now your document has
a title that will assist the screen reader in
announcing the title and document clearly, and
proper document language to pronounce words
correctly and ensure assistive technologies
deliver your content accurately.
In this section, we will use Word Styles and
review hyperlinks for accessibility. Let's
structure a document with accessible hyperlinks,
clear headings, and properly formatted lists so
screen readers can navigate with ease. To insert
an accessible hyperlink, we need to ensure that it
is clear and actionable and not just a link. Start
by selecting Insert from the menu, followed by the
Links tab. From that dropdown menu, you will select
Link. Then, another dropdown menu will appear;
select Insert Link from the bottom of that menu. A
window pops up to customize your hyperlink. Paste
the link in the space indicated to the right of
Address at the bottom of the window. The important
part is at the top of the window, where you will
enter a descriptive title such as, "Visit the
Library Website" instead of "Click Here." "Visit the
Library Website" alerts someone listening to a
screen reader that there is an actionable item in
the document.
Rather than just changing the font size, it is
important to apply true heading style.
Start at the Home tab, open the Styles group, and
select the heading level that fits your document
structure. For example, use Heading 1 for your
main title, Heading 2 for your major sections, and
Heading 3 for your sub-sections.
Bulleted or numbered lists should be formatted from
the Paragraph group. Choose your list type from
the dropdown menu: bullet, numbered, or multilevel.
For lists, always use a bulleted or numbered list
tool instead of typing symbols manually.
In this section, we will fix the color contrast
issue and make the table accessible. Design
choices can make or break accessibility. With color
contrast, text should clearly stand out from the
background, at least a 4.5 to 1 ratio for normal
text. These are a few tips to keep in mind: Word's
default theme colors, black text on white
background, already meet accessibility contrast
requirements.
Adding a table to your document always requires
using the Insert tab from the menu. Do not draw or
paste a table from another program. When you
insert your table from the Table menu tab, always
add clear header row and column data so screen
readers can identify columns in context.
Remember, accessibility isn't just compliance,
it's clarity. Your students benefit when content
is easy to see, follow, and understand.
In this section, we will add alternative text to
images and other objects.
When using images or graphics, always
include alternative text or alt text. For students
requiring a screen reader, alt text provides
assistive technologies a description of the image
represented in the document. This is especially
helpful for students with visual impairments. Be
sure to keep the description concise but
meaningful. If no alt text is provided of a chart
or graph, for example, the screen reader will only
say, "Image of a chart." This is useless for a
visually impaired student. Rather, inserting a
description like, "Chart showing enrollment
increases by 20% over five years."
For SmartArt, charts, and equations, right-click and
select Edit Alt Text to describe what's shown. If
the visual is decorative, mark it as such.
Accessible visuals ensure no learner misses the
message your content conveys.
In this section, we will run the accessibility
checker and do a quick manual review for accessibility.
Once your document is complete, go to the Review tab and click Check Accessibility.
The inspection panel will show errors, warnings,
and tips. While the inspection panel shows issues
like missing alt text, hard to read color
contrast warning, or table using merged/split cells
warnings, it does not include all requirements by
the Web Content Accessibility Guidelines.
Therefore, it is important to manually review your
document content to identify and fix accessibility
issues the checker may miss.
Headers and footers should not include essential
information because most screen readers may not
navigate to those areas. As a result, users who
rely on them may miss important content.